<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Mark Sobota (Big Huge Games) -->
<!-- edited with XML Spy v4.4 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Isaac Ellis (Big Huge Games) -->
<ROOT>
  <OFFENSIVE>
    <ENTRY name="CONQUEST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FIELD BATTLE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TACTICS">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AMBUSH">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SKIRMISH">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AIRLIFT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </OFFENSIVE>
  <DEFENSIVE>
    <ENTRY name="SURPRISE ATTACK!">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="CONQUEST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GUERRILLA WARFARE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AIRLIFT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </DEFENSIVE>
  <BARBARIAN>
    <ENTRY name="MELEE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TACTICS">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BARBARIAN RALLY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FIELD BATTLE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SUDDEN DEATH">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WHEEL AND DEAL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BARBARIANS AT THE GATES!">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="HIDEAWAY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SKIRMISH">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AIRLIFT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </BARBARIAN>
  <CUSTOM>
    <ENTRY name="LIBERATION">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SUEZ CANAL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION RICE BOWL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION BATATA">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION LOWENZAHN">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION VEREINHEITLICHUNG">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WEST COAST OFFENSIVE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF THE MIDWEST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION CARIBOU">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WARSAW OFFENSIVE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="HUNGARIAN REVOLT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="CZECH REFORM">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SKIRMISH">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="INDIA">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TOKYO DEFENSIVE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SUGAR CANE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PANAMA CANAL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AFGHANISTAN">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BAY OF PIGS">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AFRICAN CIVIL WAR">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MOSCOW">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="VIETNAM">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="INCHON">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PORK CHOP HILL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF NEW YORK">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION POTOMAC">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GUERILLA WARFARE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PACIFIC SUNRISE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION LION'S MANE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION DINGO">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION COWBOY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION SUNSET">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION PANDA">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AIRLIFT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION FEUERKUGEL">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FALKLAND CONFLICT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION PERU">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FALKLANDS CONFLICT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="OPERATION GOLDSTRIKE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF CHOSIN">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF PUSON">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF CHOSIN2">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PORK CHOP HILL2">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SKIRMISH2">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </CUSTOM>
  <ESPIONAGEUSA>
    <ENTRY name="MISSILE STRIKE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BOMB DROP">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="COUNTRYSIDE REVOLT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SEEK AND DESTROY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SAVE THE HOSTAGES">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FINAL MISSION">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </ESPIONAGEUSA>
  <ESPIONAGEUSSR>
    <ENTRY name="INFILTRATION">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BRIBERY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="COASTAL ATTACK">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TRAITORS">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GUERRILLA ACTION">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FINAL MISSION">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="COUNTER MISSILE STRIKE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </ESPIONAGEUSSR>
  <INSTRUCTIONS name="RUSSIANS">Priorities:<BULLET/>The devastation caused by World War II has left our allies in the Warsaw Pact in poor condition. We will have to rebuild their territory strength up to at least Level 3 or they are sure to switch their allegiance. Alternately, we may station our armies in their territories to quell any unrest for one turn.<BULLET/>We should focus our efforts on the Middle East, which lies in an area of great strategic importance. If we were to take it soon then we could cut the Americans off from South Asia, making it much easier to control for ourselves.<SPACE/>Victory Conditions:<BULLET/>You are engaged in a struggle with the United States for supremacy.  Win the game by destroying the Americans or by increasing your total industry income to 50 Tribute higher than that of the Americans.<SPACE/>Cold War Rules:<BULLET/>Industry - For every point of Territory Strength in each of your territores you will receive one Tribute for industry income at the end of your turn.<BULLET/>Nuclear Weapons - Up to three Nuclear Weapons can be built in each of your own territories. They may be launched at any time, but the Americans will also launch theirs. Territories that are hit by Nuclear Missiles turn into unclaimed territories.<BULLET/>Reduced Territories - Territories that have been reduced by a nuclear missile will not be available to attack for one turn.<BULLET/>Espionage Missions - In addition to battles, espionage missions can be conducted. They can be made in addition to attacking, one per turn. Winning an espionage will give you special bonuses. To begin an espionage mission click the spy icon near the minimap in the world view.<BULLET/>Diplomacy - There are no alliances in the Cold War, but nations can agree to become a client state of yours. Also, territories are not conquered, they become your client states when a successfull police action is conducted.<BULLET/>Client States - They count as your territory, but you do not receive Rare Resource income from them. These nations are not defeated, and as such can escape from your control.<BULLET/>DEFCON Meter - This measures the danger of nuclear war. Attacking the Americans, building too many Nuclear Weapons, and other factors contribute to this meter. Once the DEFCON meter reaches Level One, all Nuclear Weapons will be launched.<BULLET/>Advanced Fighters - Jet Fighters can be upgraded to Advanced Fighters after researching Information Age and Military Level 7<BULLET/>Stealth Bombers - Strategic Bombers can be upgraded to Stealth Bombers after researching Information Age and Science Level 7.</INSTRUCTIONS>
  <INSTRUCTIONS name="AMERICANS">Priorities:<BULLET/>The devastation caused by World War II has left our European allies in NATO in poor shape. We will have to rebuild their territory strength to Level 3 or they might switch their allegiance. We may not have many armies, but we can station them in these territories to settle unrest for one turn.<BULLET/>The Soviets are planning to send troops to South Korea next turn at the behest of their North Korean friends. The United Nations is also planning to send a peacekeeping force to the area, which they would like us to lead. If we fail to commit troops, we risk losing the entire peninsula to the Soviets.<SPACE/>Victory Conditions:<BULLET/>You are engaged in a struggle with the USSR for supremacy.  Win the game by destroying the Soviets or by increasing your total industry income to 50 Tribute higher than that of the Soviets.<SPACE/>Cold War Rules:<BULLET/>Industry - For every point of Territory Strength in each of your territores you will receive one Tribute for industry income at the end of your turn.<BULLET/>Nuclear Weapons - Up to three Nuclear Weapons can be built in each of your own territories. They may be launched at any time, but the Soviets will also launch theirs. Territories that are hit by Nuclear Missiles turn into unclaimed territories.<BULLET/>Reduced Territories - Territories that have been reduced by a nuclear missile will not be available to attack for one turn.<BULLET/>Espionage Missions - In addition to battles, espionage missions can be conducted. They can be made in addition to attacking, one per turn. Winning an espionage will give you special bonuses. To begin an espionage mission click the spy icon near the minimap in the world view.<BULLET/>Diplomacy - There are no alliances in the Cold War, but nations can agree to become a client state of yours. Also, territories are not conquered, they become your client states when a successfull police action is conducted.<BULLET/>Client States - They count as your territory, but you do not receive Rare Resource income from them. These nations are not defeated, and as such can escape from your control.<BULLET/>DEFCON Meter - This measures the danger of nuclear war. Attacking the Soviets, building too many Nuclear Weapons, and other factors contribute to this meter. Once the DEFCON meter reaches Level One, all Nuclear Weapons will be launched.<BULLET/>Advanced Fighters - Jet Fighters can be upgraded to Advanced Fighters after researching Information Age and Military Level 7<BULLET/>Stealth Bombers - Strategic Bombers can be upgraded to Stealth Bombers after researching Information Age and Science Level 7.</INSTRUCTIONS>
  <INTRO_TEXT>
    <ENTRY name="INTRO_TEXT">The Cold War rose directly out of the ashes of World War II. The United States and the Soviet Union were never completely amicable towards each other, only allies of convenience against the Nazi threat. Once Hitler was defeated, both sides began competing for influence around the world. The two powers conducted proxy wars instead of engaging each other in direct military conflict. Neither side wished to actively engage the other in a “hot war”, for fear of an all-out nuclear war, hence the term “cold war”.<SPACE/>However, even with the war being cold, both sides found various other ways to compete with each other. The most horrific was the arms race, in which both sides began stockpiling nuclear weapons and extending the range of their missiles. Both sides conducted extensive espionage missions against each other. One positive result of this competition was the Space Race. The Soviets were the first in space, but the Americans won the race to the moon. Both sides benefited from the new technologies that were required to accomplish these amazing feats.<SPACE/>Another aspect of this war was the formation of military alliances. The Americans joined with Western Europe to form the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). In response the Soviets created the Warsaw Pact, which brought together most of Eastern Europe into a common defensive bloc. If any member of these coalitions were to be attacked, all of the other members would immediately come to the aid of the nation that was in trouble.<SPACE/>While all-out war never broke out, it came close on several occasions, never more so than during the Cuban Missile crisis. The crisis broke out when the Americans discovered that the Soviets had begun installing Nuclear Missiles in Cuba, only 90 miles off the coast of the United States. Even worse, more missiles were being imported for installation. The United States President, Kennedy, acted decisively and achieved a diplomatic resolution that caused the Soviets to pull their missiles out of Cuba.<SPACE/>In the end it was America’s economy that triumphed over the Soviets manpower. Communism was a failure in the Soviet Union, as even before the Union’s collapse many communist policies had long been abandoned. The Warsaw Pact has dissolved, but NATO lives on today and has even begun adding members from the former Soviet bloc.</ENTRY>
  </INTRO_TEXT>
</ROOT>
