<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Mark Sobota (Big Huge Games) -->
<!-- edited with XML Spy v4.4 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Isaac Ellis (Big Huge Games) -->
<ROOT>
  <OFFENSIVE>
    <ENTRY name="CONQUEST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FIELD BATTLE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SUPPLY TRAIN">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="HIDEAWAY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </OFFENSIVE>
  <DEFENSIVE>
    <ENTRY name="GUERRILLA WARFARE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="CONQUEST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </DEFENSIVE>
  <BARBARIAN>
    <ENTRY name="MELEE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TACTICS">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="NOMAD">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="HIDEAWAY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </BARBARIAN>
  <CUSTOM>
    <ENTRY name="ISTANBUL">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ANKARA">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AUSTERLITZ">
      <STRING>Upon learning of the Austrian defeat at Ulm, a Bavarian town located on the north bank of the Danube, the Russian army under General Kutusov retreated to the river’s north bank. In a series of rear-guard actions, Kutosov broke off engagement with the French forces and arrived at the Moravian town of Olmutz in mid-November. Part of the French army, commanded by Marshal Murat, followed in close pursuit, finally halting east of the city of Brunn at the town of Austerlitz. By mid-November, Napoleon, after receiving the surrender of Vienna (and after Beethoven had removed Napoleon’s name from his Third Symphony as punishment!), began to concentrate his forces in the hope of forcing a major battle.<SPACE/>This hope was fulfilled with the arrival of the young Tsar Alexander with a second Russian army at the camp of the combined Allied army. Regardless of Kutusov’s desire to await further reinforcements, or at worst retreat east to the Carpathian Mountains, Alexander had declared war on France to rid Europe of the so-called “Corsican Ogre” (Napoleon), and he now intended to do just that.<SPACE/>Thus, the Allied army was irrevocably committed to an offensive, and this began with an advance towards Austerlitz in November. This advance led to the battle of Austerlitz (later also known as the Battle of the Three Emperors for Napoleon, Alexander, and Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor) on December 2, 1805. The French victory, a military masterpiece, effectively destroyed the Allied army. After just one battle, Alexander apparently had his fill of being a battlefield commander, and the day after Austerlitz he met with Francis and informed him he was taking his Russians and going home.<SPACE/>There was nothing left for Francis to do but to treat with Napoleon. A few days later Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor, became Emperor Francis I of Austria. The Treaty of Pressburg (modern Bratislava) called for his nation’s withdrawal from the Third Coalition, and also took substantial territories from Austria. It reinforced the previous treaties of Campo Formio and Luneville that acknowledged the ceding of Austrian holdings in Italy and Bavaria. Additional lands were ceded to Bavaria, Wurtemberg and Baden, and Austrian claims on those states were specifically renounced. Austria paid an indemnity of 40 million francs. Finally, the Holy Roman Empire, such as it existed at this point, was formally dissolved. Subsequently, Napoleon created the Confederation of the Rhine, which included the territories renounced by Austria.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AUSTERLITZ2">
      <STRING>Upon learning of the Austrian defeat at Ulm, a Bavarian town located on the north bank of the Danube, the Russian army under General Kutusov retreated to the river’s north bank. In a series of rear-guard actions, Kutosov broke off engagement with the French forces and arrived at the Moravian town of Olmutz in mid-November. Part of the French army, commanded by Marshal Murat, followed in close pursuit, finally halting east of the city of Brunn at the town of Austerlitz. By mid-November, Napoleon, after receiving the surrender of Vienna (and after Beethoven had removed Napoleon’s name from his Third Symphony as punishment!), began to concentrate his forces in the hope of forcing a major battle.<SPACE/>This hope was fulfilled with the arrival of the young Tsar Alexander with a second Russian army at the camp of the combined Allied army. Regardless of Kutusov’s desire to await further reinforcements, or at worst retreat east to the Carpathian Mountains, Alexander had declared war on France to rid Europe of the so-called “Corsican Ogre” (Napoleon), and he now intended to do just that.<SPACE/>Thus, the Allied army was irrevocably committed to an offensive, and this began with an advance towards Austerlitz in November. This advance led to the battle of Austerlitz (later also known as the Battle of the Three Emperors for Napoleon, Alexander, and Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor) on December 2, 1805. The French victory, a military masterpiece, effectively destroyed the Allied army. After just one battle, Alexander apparently had his fill of being a battlefield commander, and the day after Austerlitz he met with Francis and informed him he was taking his Russians and going home.<SPACE/>There was nothing left for Francis to do but to treat with Napoleon. A few days later Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor, became Emperor Francis I of Austria. The Treaty of Pressburg (modern Bratislava) called for his nation’s withdrawal from the Third Coalition, and also took substantial territories from Austria. It reinforced the previous treaties of Campo Formio and Luneville that acknowledged the ceding of Austrian holdings in Italy and Bavaria. Additional lands were ceded to Bavaria, Wurtemberg and Baden, and Austrian claims on those states were specifically renounced. Austria paid an indemnity of 40 million francs. Finally, the Holy Roman Empire, such as it existed at this point, was formally dissolved. Subsequently, Napoleon created the Confederation of the Rhine, which included the territories renounced by Austria.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="AUSTERLITZ3">
      <STRING>Upon learning of the Austrian defeat at Ulm, a Bavarian town located on the north bank of the Danube, the Russian army under General Kutusov retreated to the river’s north bank. In a series of rear-guard actions, Kutosov broke off engagement with the French forces and arrived at the Moravian town of Olmutz in mid-November. Part of the French army, commanded by Marshal Murat, followed in close pursuit, finally halting east of the city of Brunn at the town of Austerlitz. By mid-November, Napoleon, after receiving the surrender of Vienna (and after Beethoven had removed Napoleon’s name from his Third Symphony as punishment!), began to concentrate his forces in the hope of forcing a major battle.<SPACE/>This hope was fulfilled with the arrival of the young Tsar Alexander with a second Russian army at the camp of the combined Allied army. Regardless of Kutusov’s desire to await further reinforcements, or at worst retreat east to the Carpathian Mountains, Alexander had declared war on France to rid Europe of the so-called “Corsican Ogre” (Napoleon), and he now intended to do just that.<SPACE/>Thus, the Allied army was irrevocably committed to an offensive, and this began with an advance towards Austerlitz in November. This advance led to the battle of Austerlitz (later also known as the Battle of the Three Emperors for Napoleon, Alexander, and Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor) on December 2, 1805. The French victory, a military masterpiece, effectively destroyed the Allied army. After just one battle, Alexander apparently had his fill of being a battlefield commander, and the day after Austerlitz he met with Francis and informed him he was taking his Russians and going home.<SPACE/>There was nothing left for Francis to do but to treat with Napoleon. A few days later Francis II, the Holy Roman Emperor, became Emperor Francis I of Austria. The Treaty of Pressburg (modern Bratislava) called for his nation’s withdrawal from the Third Coalition, and also took substantial territories from Austria. It reinforced the previous treaties of Campo Formio and Luneville that acknowledged the ceding of Austrian holdings in Italy and Bavaria. Additional lands were ceded to Bavaria, Wurtemberg and Baden, and Austrian claims on those states were specifically renounced. Austria paid an indemnity of 40 million francs. Finally, the Holy Roman Empire, such as it existed at this point, was formally dissolved. Subsequently, Napoleon created the Confederation of the Rhine, which included the territories renounced by Austria.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="LEIPZIG">
      <STRING>Although Napoleon had married the daughter of Emperor Francis I of Austria in 1810, that did not stop Francis from declaring war on Napoleon in 1813.  Napoleon soon tasted defeat at the Battle of Leipzig, also known as the Battle of Nations. The forces allied against France continued their march, and Paris fell in 1814. Napoleon was exiled to Elba, and Louis XVIII, brother of the executed Louis XVI, was placed on the throne.
</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="JENA">
      <STRING>It was France’s increasing influence over the Germanic States which caused France to go to war with Prussia in 1806. The Prussian army was handily defeated by Napoleon at the battles of Jena and Auerstadt that year, leaving Berlin open for the taking. Thus, Prussia was taken out of the equation of great powers in Europe.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="EYLAU">
      <STRING>Prussia left the First Coalition in April 1795, and, under the terms of the Treaty of Basel, remained neutral through the wars of the Second and Third Coalitions, ignoring the violation of its territory during the Ulm campaign. Though its army had performed less than efficiently in 1794, Prussia remained blissfully, and wrongly, confident in its belief that its troops were superior to those of the French. <SPACE/>By 1806, Prussia had a number of unresolved grievances and disagreements with France regarding its hegemony over the disposition of the Rhine states, most particularly Hanover. With the encouragement of England and the assurance of the support of the Russian army, Prussia entered into the Fourth Coalition when it declared war on France in October 1806. This declaration gave Napoleon the opportunity to settle his disputes with Prussia. The whirlwind campaign of October and November, which included the double battle of Jena-Auerstadt, destroyed the bulk of the Prussian army and led to the French occupation of Berlin. <SPACE/>Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December, the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26, the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. <SPACE/>The following June, Napoleon at first rebuffed the advance of the Russian army and then advanced on the Russian position at Heilsburg. After a desultory battle in which each side suffered over 10,000 casualties, the French withdrew and undertook to outmaneuver the Russians. The Russian army commander also withdrew, but with the intention of placing his army between Napoleon and the French corps besieging Konigsberg. On June 14 the Russians crossed the Alle at Friedland and began to push in against an isolated corps under the command of Marshal Lannes. However, within a few hours it became evident that Lannes was being reinforced. At a little after noon Napoleon arrived on the battlefield to find the best of all worlds--the Russian army on the wrong side of the river with its front divided by a not easily fordable stream. At 5:30 p.m. the French launched their attack and quickly wrecked the Russians’ left flank, pushing their units against the Alle. With many soldiers drowning in their attempts to swim to the right bank of the Alle, the Russians lost over 20,000 casualties while the French lost less than half of that number.<SPACE/>This defeat led to the Treaties of Tilsit of July 7-9, 1807. These agreements between France, Russia and Prussia ended the Fourth Coalition. The Tsar recognized the Confederation of the Rhine, now augmented by a “Kingdom of Westphalia” made up of former Prussian territories west of the Elbe, with Jerome Bonaparte as king.  Prussian Poland was formed into a Grand Duchy of Warsaw, with the Elector (henceforth "King ") of Saxony as its ruler. Russia was to observe the Berlin Decree.<SPACE/>Napoleon and Tsar Alexander also secretly agreed that if Great Britain continued to deny them “freedom of the seas,” they would call on Denmark, Sweden and Portugal to close their ports to British shipping, and would make war on any of the three that refused. They also agreed that France could have access to the Danish fleet. After ceding territory, Prussia was reduced to four provinces and its army was correspondingly reduced.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WAGRAM">
      <STRING>Defeated in 1796 and 1800, and humiliated in 1805, Austria desired not only revenge but also the opportunity to regain its lost provinces, which had been incorporated into the French puppet state, the Kingdom of  Italy. An opportunity came with the French invasion of Spain in 1808 and the installation of Joseph Bonaparte, Napoleon’s brother, as its king. Political and monetary encouragement combined with the dissatisfaction of a Europe dominated by France as well as the French invasion of Spain, led Austria to join Great Britain in the Fifth Coalition.<SPACE/>The main theater of war was the Danube. The Austrian main army was commanded by her best general, Francis’ brother, Archduke Charles (Karl).  In April, Charles invaded Bavaria only to be stymied by the French general on the spot, Marshal Davout, and then defeated by Napoleon in a series of battles known collectively as Abensburg-Eckmuhl. This defeat forced Charles to withdraw to the north bank of the Danube, leaving Vienna to be occupied for a second time by the French.<SPACE/>On May 22, Napoleon began to cross his army to the north bank of the Danube between the towns of Aspern and Essling. This led to a desperate battle that lasted for two days and resulted in the defeat and withdrawal of the French to the south bank. Aspern-Essling, as the battle came to be known, was Napoleon’s first clear-cut defeat in Europe.<SPACE/>On the other fronts, an Austrian army invaded the Kingdom of Italy, but after an initial success was defeated and forced to retreat north of the Alps. Another Austrian army moved into the Duchy of Warsaw, defeating the Polish army. Finally, Austria encouraged a revolt in the Alpine province of Tyrol, which had been ceded to Bavaria in 1805. <SPACE/>By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder.<SPACE/>That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat.<SPACE/>After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Francis sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SYRIA">
      <STRING>After Napoleon’s humiliation upon the defeat of his fleet by Lord Nelson in Egypt, Napoleon marched his army to Syria in an attempt to compensate for his loss. There, Napoleon was defeated by the Ottoman general Djezzar, and had to march back to Egypt. Soon after his return, he fled back to Paris, leaving Egypt in command of one of his officers. It was upon his return that Napoleon overthrew the Directorate in what is known as the Coup of Brumaire, with help from Talleyrand - a Bishop and former foreign minister of France. Napoleon then assumed dictatorial control of France as first consul, and appointed Talleyrand as his foreign minister.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MANTUA">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MANTUA2">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MANTUA3">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MALTA">
      <STRING>Before Napoleon arrived at the island of Malta, the island had been conquered by the Knights of the Order of St. John during the Crusades. Many had tried to conquer the Knights and failed. Napoleon came to the island in 1798 while en route to a great victory in Egypt, even as the British fleet under the command of Lord Nelson sailed the Mediterranean in search of him. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MALTA2">
      <STRING>Before Napoleon arrived at the island of Malta, the island had been conquered by the Knights of the Order of St. John during the Crusades. Many had tried to conquer the Knights and failed. Napoleon came to the island in 1798 while en route to a great victory in Egypt, even as the British fleet under the command of Lord Nelson sailed the Mediterranean in search of him. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MALTA3">
      <STRING>Before Napoleon arrived at the island of Malta, the island had been conquered by the Knights of the Order of St. John during the Crusades. Many had tried to conquer the Knights and failed. Napoleon came to the island in 1798 while en route to a great victory in Egypt, even as the British fleet under the command of Lord Nelson sailed the Mediterranean in search of him. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="LODI">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic, and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition. The Coalition included Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera between Genoa and Nice. They had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula when, in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign launched one month later, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May, the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war. <SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault, which forced Napoleon into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola, and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austrian Empire—the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna. <SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FRIEDLAND">
      <STRING>Historically, the defeat of the Russians at Friedland led to the Treaties of Tilsit of July 7-9, 1807. With these agreements between France, Russia and Prussia, the Fourth Coalition came to an end. The Tsar recognized the Confederation of the Rhine, now augmented by a “Kingdom of Westphalia” made up of former Prussian territories west of the Elbe, with Jerome Bonaparte as king. Prussian Poland was formed into a Grand Duchy of Warsaw, with the Elector (henceforth "King ") of Saxony as its ruler. Russia was to observe the Berlin Decree. <SPACE/>Napoleon and Alexander also secretly agreed that if  Great Britain continued to deny the “freedom of the seas” they would call on Denmark, Sweden and Portugal to close their ports to British shipping, and would make war on any of the three that refused. They also agreed that France could have access to the Danish fleet. After ceding territory, Prussia was reduced to four provinces and its army was correspondingly reduced.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="CORSICA">
      <STRING>The city of Ajaccio on the island of Corsica was the place of Napoleon’s birth in 1769, and the ancestral home of his family.  France annexed the island the same year, and many were unhappy about it, causing civil war. The leader of the rebels was Pascale di Paoli, Napoleon's childhood hero. Napoleon wished to join the rebels himself, but it was believed that his family was pro-French so his family was forced to flee to France.  </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="KEEPING THE PEACE">
      <STRING>Although Louis XVI of France did not survive the French Revolution, his kin did, leaving hope for those who wished for a return to the monarchy of old. The Royalists were mainly the former elite who were not satisfied with the new social order in France. They longed for a return to the days of the king doling out favors to them and their relatives. While they never gained control of a province outright, the French Royalists did manage to cause trouble in France. In 1795, the Royalists tried to overthrow the Directorate, but failed thanks in no small part to Napoleon. They did manage to throw quite the wrench into various machinations of the revolution, but once Napoleon took power their influence diminished.
</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PORTUGAL">
      <STRING>General Junot and a small French army occupied Lisbon on November 30, 1807. Three days earlier, Regent John of Portugal had sailed for Brazil. In August 1808, a small British army under the command of Sir Arthur Wellesley (later to be known as the famed Duke of Wellington) went ashore in Portugal. The British defeated the French at Rolica and Vimiero. The French then evacuated Lisbon according to the Convention of Cintra, signed August 30, 1808.<SPACE/>After the British occupied Lisbon that August, General Burrard, who had signed the Convention of Cintra for them, was recalled, leaving Sir John Moore in command. Moore moved his small army to Salamanca. Upon hearing that the Spanish in Madrid were holding out against the French, he advanced on that city. Napoleon, who was now on the Peninsula, swept around Moore’s flank and prevented him from retreating to Lisbon. This led to the hurried and harried retreat to Corunna, a port in northwestern Spain, and a subsequent evacuation. Moore was killed in the defensive battle, but the French decision to follow him assured that Lisbon would not be occupied before the British could land reinforcements.<SPACE/>In April 1809, Wellesley returned to Lisbon as the commander of the British army. On May 12 he attacked Marshal Soult at Oporto and forced the French to precipitously retreat through the mountains, abandoning their artillery in order to escape capture. Wellesley then advanced on Madrid in support of the Spanish army, which was in open revolt against the French. He rendezvoused with a Spanish army of 34,000 led by General Cuesta, but was forced to retreat his own troops in the face of the advance of an army under the command of Napoleon's brother, King Joseph.<SPACE/>Wellesley barely defeated the French at Talavera on June 28, 1809, and fortunately withdrew just in time to avoid being cut off from Portugal by an army led by Marshal Soult. This ended the campaign in Spain and Portugal in 1809.<SPACE/>In 1810, Napoleon appointed Marshal Massena to command an army of 80,000 to invade and capture Lisbon and drive the British from the Peninsula. On September 27, 1810, Wellesley defeated the French at Busaco.  Regardless, Massena outflanked his position and continued his march to Lisbon, only to find it defended by the so-called Lines of Torres Vedras, an impregnable triple line of forts with the Atlantic Ocean on its left flank and the Tagus River on its right.<SPACE/>Massena remained in front of this fortified position from October 1810 until March 1811, when due to lack of supplies and attrition, he was forced to retreat back into Spain. As Wellesley advanced he laid siege to the French garrison in the fortress of Almeida. Massena’s advance to resupply the fortress brought on the Battle of Fuentes de Onoro, which occurred between May 3 and 5, 1810.  During this battle the British were outflanked and, but for Marshal Bessieries’ refusal to commit the Guard Cavalry, would have been defeated. But as usual--in this campaign--the French could not quite achieve a victory, and the battle ended in another French defeat and the withdrawal of Massena’s army.<SPACE/>On May 16, a British army commanded by General Beresford fought and defeated a French attempt to relieve the fortress at Badajoz led by Marshal Soult. Though the siege continued, the high casualty rate caused great controversy and Beresford never again commanded an independent army in battle.<SPACE/>In 1812, Wellington once again advanced from Portugal, capturing the fortresses of Almeida and Badajoz. He was opposed by Marshal Massena who commanded a cobbled-together army which was short of cavalry and artillery. In a series of maneuvers, Massena’s army out-marched and out-maneuvered Wellesley for over two weeks. Then, just as Wellesley was about to retreat into Portugal, the French over-extended their march, giving the British an opportunity to attack. The resulting Battle of Salamanca was a French disaster of the first order, which led to a retreat and evacuation of Madrid. Wellington then mistakenly followed the retreat and extended his line of communications beyond good sense. Soon every French army in Spain was converging on the British army. Just in time the British retreated back to the safety of Portugal, but only after the army came perilously close to falling apart. As it was, the army suffered horrific losses due to attrition and desertions.<SPACE/>In 1813, Wellesley returned with a vengeance, capturing Madrid once and for all and forcing Joseph to retreat with his army. Joseph’s decision to stand and fight was a mistake that led to the Defeat at Vittoria--leading Beethoven, who had long since ceased to be a fan of Napoleon’s, to compose  his symphony “Wellington’s Victory.”</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MADRID">
      <STRING>A member of the First Coalition until 1795, Spain then becam an ally of France. In 1805, Spain joined her fleet with that of France, but, under the command of the French Admirl Villeneuve, suffered a disastrous defeat at the hads of Admiral Lord Nelson at the Battle of Trafalgar. In 1807. the Spanish King Charles IV (who was not much more than a figurehead at this point) was persuaded to allow the French to march through Spain in order to reach Portugal.<SPACE/>The establishment of French bases in Spain caused unrest and subsequently led to the king's summons to a conference with Napoleon in Bayonne. During this conference, Spain's entire family was placed under house arrest, and then replaced on the Spanish throne by Napoleon's brother, Joseph. This led not only to the Spanish army but also the people themselves rebelling against French rule.<SPACE/>This rebellion was based on an inherent xenophobia combined with a very strong religious hatred for the secularism of the French Revolution. After four years of insurrection, Joseph was forced to evacuate Spain, laying the foundation for the return of the Bourbons.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BRITTANY">
      <STRING>This region, known as Armorica in ancient times, was conquered by Julius Caesar and incorporated into Gaul. The region became known as Brittany after Britons settled there after being driven out of Britain by the Anglo-Saxons in the 6th century A.D. After their arrival, much of the history of Brittany involved its people fighting for their independence from England and France. The peasants of Brittany never acquiesced to centralized rule, and it was one of the first regions to revolt during the French Revolution, though it did not join the revolution in Paris.
</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BELGIUM">
      <STRING>In 1793, Revolutionary France declared war on the Dutch Republic, a curious decision considering that Holland had been a self-ruling republic for over 200 years, rather than a monarchy as were all the other foes of the Revolution. After defeating the Austrian army in Belgium at the battles of Wattignes and Fleurus, France conquered Holland in 1795, gaining access to its fleet. <SPACE/>The French-established Batavian Republic marked the transition to a more efficient government modeled after that in France, of which Holland was now a vassal state. The only political instability came in the form of two coups, in 1798 and 1801, both instigated by the French. In 1806, Napoleon installed his brother Louis as King of Holland and Belgium. In 1810, after Louis proved a failure as king, Napoleon dissolved the kingdom and incorporated Holland into France.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WATERLOO">
      <STRING>During Napoleon’s exile to the island of Elba, the alliance against him collapsed at the Congress of Vienna, and Napoleon used this as his opportunity to re-enter the Continent. He landed a force in southern France and marched his way to Paris. The allies banded together against him once more, leaving Napoleon only one option – to meet them in battle. Napoleon decided to take the battle to the allies at Waterloo, but was defeated by Lord Wellington, who led the combined British and Prussian forces. Napoleon was then exiled for a second and final time. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GREAT BRITAIN">
      <STRING>While Napoleon never actually invaded Great Britain, he did plan to invade it many times. In 1797 he drew up plans to invade England and was then given command of France’s Army of England. Upon taking command, he realized the folly of the plan and returned to Paris. He spent many resources and much time on building a fleet large enough to transport his army across the channel. However, instead of listening to the admiral in charge of the navy, who advocated building a smaller, yet higher quality fleet, Napoleon built a large fleet of ships that were hardly seaworthy, which ended up being a huge mistake. There were reports that a test launch of one of the boats actually cost Napoleon many of his own men, and the boat ended up sinking.<SPACE/>What finally ended Napoleon’s great navy was the Battle of Trafalgar, in which Britain, led by Lord Nelson, defeated much of the French and Spanish fleets. Rather than waste any more resources on the endeavor, Napoleon gave up on his plan to invade the British Isles and marched his army east towards Austria.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="PYRAMIDS">
      <STRING>Napoleon had gained much fame in his conquests of Italy. Many political leaders in France tried to figure out how to use Napoleon's fame to gain power. Unfortunately for them, Napoleon was not interested in being someone else's pawn. He wanted power himself, and realized that if he accomplished one more great victory he would be able to declare himself emperor. It was in this climate that Napoleon embarked on his attack on Egypt from Toulon in May of 1798.<SPACE/>Napoleon had at first dismissed the idea recommended to him by a friend. However, as it became clearer to him that he needed a great victory, he decided that Egypt was where it could be achieved. Arriving off the coast of Alexandria, Napoleon quickly took control of Egypt's cities. Knowing he was in a hostile environment, he made sure to give a great deal of freedom to the conquered Egyptians. Since the Mameluke leaders of Egypt had been appointed by the Ottoman Turks, Napoleon made the claim that by conquering Egypt he was actually freeing the Egyptians from captivity. Napoleon instituted many civil reforms in Egypt while he was there. However, by August 1798 Lord Nelson finally caught up with Napoleon after chasing him across the Mediterranean, and scuttled Napoleon’s fleet at Abukir Bay, severing Napoleon’s link to France.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="RUSSIA">
      <STRING>Upon Russia’s refusal to close its ports to British goods, Napoleon, feeling confident after recent victories, marched on Moscow in 1812. He quickly marched across Russia expecting to find much resistance, but instead General Barclay had ordered his troops to not confront Napoleon. Tsar Alexander I, fed up with General Barclay’s reluctance to confront Napoleon, relieved him and put General Kutosov in charge of the Russian armies. Kutosov finally attacked the French army at the city of Borodino. However, Napoleon was not deterred, and soon arrived in Moscow, where he found that the Russians had abandoned the city. <SPACE/>The Tsar and his government had fled to St. Petersburg. Once Napoleon moved into the city, a few Russians who had stayed behind lit the city on fire, destroying any accomplishment that Napoleon wished to achieve. Napoleon desperately wanted to combat the Russian army in hopes that a decisive victory would lead to Alexander capitulating, but the Russian armies would not commit to such a battle. After a month in Moscow, Napoleon gave up hopes of conquering Russia and ordered his troops to retreat. The road home was not an easy one. The countryside had been stripped bare and the weather was harsh. Any soldiers that strayed from the main column were swiftly cut down by marauding Cossacks. Napoleon arrived back in Paris having lost the army of 500,000 men with which he had originally set off with to the cruel Russian winter.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF STOCKHOLM">
      <STRING>While Napoleon never actually attacked Sweden, he did encounter them in numerous battles. Jean Bernadotte, one of Napoleon’s generals, made a good impression on the Swedes when negotiating peace with them. Later, when the Swedes found themselves without a suitable heir, Bernadotte was adopted by the ruling Charles XIII. Bernadotte later helped defeat Napoleon at the Battle of Leipzig. In 1814, he marched into Denmark and forced the Danes to hand Norway over to him. Once this was approved by the great powers at the Congress of Vienna, Norway and Sweden were united into one kingdom, with Bernadotte being elevated on to the throne as Charles XIV.  </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="NEW MONTENOTTE">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="MONTENOTTE4">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty, Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France. The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close. Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the Battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather. By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Archduke Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder. That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat. After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna near the end of 1809 which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Emperor Franz I sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="EMBARGO OF COPENHAGEN">
      <STRING>Denmark was part of the Armed Neutrality of the North, along with Sweden, Russia and Prussia, who decided they would band together to stop the British from stopping and searching their trading ships. The alliance fell apart when in 1807 Lord Nelson led the British fleet at Copenhagen and destroyed the Danish fleet. The British then used Copenhagen as the trade nexus of their goods onto the continent, thereby thwarting Napoleon’s Continental System.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF COPENHAGEN">
      <STRING>Denmark was part of the Armed Neutrality of the North along with Sweden, Russia and Prussia. These nations banded together to stop the British from stopping and searching their trading ships. However, the alliance fell apart in 1807 when Lord Nelson led the British fleet at Copenhagen and destroyed the Danish fleet. The British then used Copenhagen as the trade nexus of their goods onto the continent, thereby thwarting Napoleon’s Continental System.   </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF TIVOLI">
      <STRING>Pope Pius VI hated the Revolution for its anti-religious tenets. Napoleon had him arrested and brought to France, where he died in 1800. In 1800, a new Pope was named—Pius VII. The new Pope immediately undertook negotiations to improve relations between the French government and the Church. This agreement, signed in July 1801, was known as the Concordat of 1801.<SPACE/> In 1804, Pius VII traveled to Paris to participate in the coronation of Napoleon as Emperor. Subsequently, the Concordat fell apart. Pius refused to annul Joseph’s Bonaparte’s marriage and he also opposed the Continental system. In 1808, partly in response to these facts, a French army occupied the Papal States. Pius excommunicated all concerned, and he in turn was promptly arrested and ultimately confined at Fontainbleau where he was required to negotiate a new concordat. With Napoleon’s defeat, Pius was returned to Rome, and the Congress of Vienna ultimately restored the Papal States to the Pope.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF ULM">
      <STRING>After a very short peace following Napoleon’s defeat of the Second Coalition in 1800, in 1803 Great Britain declared war on France. For the next two years Prime Minister William Pitt (the Younger) worked to convince the major continental powers to join Great Britain in making war on France. Using the political situation and the desire of Austria to regain its Italian provinces and English money, in the summer of 1805 he persuaded Russia and Austria to join Britain and a number of minor powers, including Sweden, in a Third Coalition. The plan was to field half a million soldiers in armies located in Northern Italy, the Rhine and the North Sea to overwhelm and defeat Napoleon. What occurred was somewhat different.<SPACE/>From 1803 to late summer 1805, the bulk of the French field army was in camps around the Channel port of Boulogne, training and preparing for an invasion of England. Stymied by the Royal Navy, when Napoleon learned of the Third Coalition he immediately began to transfer his army from the Channel to concentrate on the Rhine. Meanwhile, an Austrian army advanced to Ulm, a Bavarian town located on the north bank of the Danube, with the intent of blocking a French advance on Vienna while awaiting the arrival of the Russian armies.<SPACE/>But Napoleon did not wait for the Russians. Instead, in a series of forced marches the  Grande Armee (as it was now known) encircled the Austrians and forced the surrender of 90,000 men without a shot being fired, in one of the most masterful and successful campaigns in history. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE FOR PORTUGAL">
      <STRING>General Junot and a small French army occupied Lisbon on November 30, 1807. Three days earlier, Regent John of Portugal had sailed for Brazil. In August 1808, a small British army under the command of Sir Arthur Wellesley (later to be known as the famed Duke of Wellington) went ashore in Portugal. The British defeated the French at Rolica and Vimiero. The French then evacuated Lisbon according to the Convention of Cintra, signed August 30, 1808.<SPACE/>After the British occupied Lisbon that August, General Burrard, who had signed the Convention of Cintra for them, was recalled, leaving Sir John Moore in command. Moore moved his small army to Salamanca. Upon hearing that the Spanish in Madrid were holding out against the French, he advanced on that city. Napoleon, who was now on the Peninsula, swept around Moore’s flank and prevented him from retreating to Lisbon. This led to the hurried and harried retreat to Corunna, a port in northwestern Spain, and a subsequent evacuation. Moore was killed in the defensive battle, but the French decision to follow him assured that Lisbon would not be occupied before the British could land reinforcements.<SPACE/>In April 1809, Wellesley returned to Lisbon as the commander of the British army. On May 12 he attacked Marshal Soult at Oporto and forced the French to precipitously retreat through the mountains, abandoning their artillery in order to escape capture. Wellesley then advanced on Madrid in support of the Spanish army, which was in open revolt against the French. He rendezvoused with a Spanish army of 34,000 led by General Cuesta, but was forced to retreat his own troops in the face of the advance of an army under the command of Napoleon's brother, King Joseph.<SPACE/>Wellesley barely defeated the French at Talavera on June 28, 1809, and fortunately withdrew just in time to avoid being cut off from Portugal by an army led by Marshal Soult. This ended the campaign in Spain and Portugal in 1809.<SPACE/>In 1810, Napoleon appointed Marshal Massena to command an army of 80,000 to invade and capture Lisbon and drive the British from the Peninsula. On September 27, 1810, Wellesley defeated the French at Busaco.  Regardless, Massena outflanked his position and continued his march to Lisbon, only to find it defended by the so-called Lines of Torres Vedras, an impregnable triple line of forts with the Atlantic Ocean on its left flank and the Tagus River on its right.<SPACE/>Massena remained in front of this fortified position from October 1810 until March 1811, when due to lack of supplies and attrition, he was forced to retreat back into Spain. As Wellesley advanced he laid siege to the French garrison in the fortress of Almeida. Massena’s advance to resupply the fortress brought on the Battle of Fuentes de Onoro, which occurred between May 3 and 5, 1810.  During this battle the British were outflanked and, but for Marshal Bessieries’ refusal to commit the Guard Cavalry, would have been defeated. But as usual--in this campaign--the French could not quite achieve a victory, and the battle ended in another French defeat and the withdrawal of Massena’s army.<SPACE/>On May 16, a British army commanded by General Beresford fought and defeated a French attempt to relieve the fortress at Badajoz led by Marshal Soult. Though the siege continued, the high casualty rate caused great controversy and Beresford never again commanded an independent army in battle.<SPACE/>In 1812, Wellington once again advanced from Portugal, capturing the fortresses of Almeida and Badajoz. He was opposed by Marshal Massena who commanded a cobbled-together army which was short of cavalry and artillery. In a series of maneuvers, Massena’s army out-marched and out-maneuvered Wellesley for over two weeks. Then, just as Wellesley was about to retreat into Portugal, the French over-extended their march, giving the British an opportunity to attack. The resulting Battle of Salamanca was a French disaster of the first order, which led to a retreat and evacuation of Madrid. Wellington then mistakenly followed the retreat and extended his line of communications beyond good sense. Soon every French army in Spain was converging on the British army. Just in time the British retreated back to the safety of Portugal, but only after the army came perilously close to falling apart. As it was, the army suffered horrific losses due to attrition and desertions.<SPACE/>In 1813, Wellesley returned with a vengeance, capturing Madrid once and for all and forcing Joseph to retreat with his army. Joseph’s decision to stand and fight was a mistake that led to the Defeat at Vittoria--leading Beethoven, who had long since ceased to be a fan of Napoleon’s, to compose  his symphony “Wellington’s Victory.”</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ISTANBUL2">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ISTANBUL3">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ANKARA2">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ANKARA3">
      <STRING>Napoleon never actually marched on the Ottoman Turks’ capital, mainly due to the fact that the resources required were far beyond his reach, even though a shortage of resources had never stopped him before. Also, the Ottoman Turks were usually good friends of the British, as the British continually supported them in their struggles against Russia and in Egypt. However, Napoleon was more interested in defeating the British, and did not want to involve the Turks if he could avoid it. The Ottoman Empire was too big for the Turks to control, and it eventually collapsed, as state after state received its independence. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WAGRAM2">
      <STRING>Defeated in 1796 and 1800, and humiliated in 1805, Austria desired not only revenge but also the opportunity to regain its lost provinces, which had been incorporated into the French puppet state, the Kingdom of  Italy. An opportunity came with the French invasion of Spain in 1808 and the installation of Joseph Bonaparte, Napoleon’s brother, as its king. Political and monetary encouragement combined with the dissatisfaction of a Europe dominated by France as well as the French invasion of Spain, led Austria to join Great Britain in the Fifth Coalition.<SPACE/>The main theater of war was the Danube. The Austrian main army was commanded by her best general, Francis’ brother, Archduke Charles (Karl).  In April, Charles invaded Bavaria only to be stymied by the French general on the spot, Marshal Davout, and then defeated by Napoleon in a series of battles known collectively as Abensburg-Eckmuhl. This defeat forced Charles to withdraw to the north bank of the Danube, leaving Vienna to be occupied for a second time by the French.<SPACE/>On May 22, Napoleon began to cross his army to the north bank of the Danube between the towns of Aspern and Essling. This led to a desperate battle that lasted for two days and resulted in the defeat and withdrawal of the French to the south bank. Aspern-Essling, as the battle came to be known, was Napoleon’s first clear-cut defeat in Europe.<SPACE/>On the other fronts, an Austrian army invaded the Kingdom of Italy, but after an initial success was defeated and forced to retreat north of the Alps. Another Austrian army moved into the Duchy of Warsaw, defeating the Polish army. Finally, Austria encouraged a revolt in the Alpine province of the Tyrol, which had been ceded to Bavaria in 1805. <SPACE/>By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder.<SPACE/>That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat.<SPACE/>After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Francis sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="WAGRAM3">
      <STRING>Defeated in 1796 and 1800, and humiliated in 1805, Austria desired not only revenge but also the opportunity to regain its lost provinces, which had been incorporated into the French puppet state, the Kingdom of  Italy. An opportunity came with the French invasion of Spain in 1808 and the installation of Joseph Bonaparte, Napoleon’s brother, as its king. Political and monetary encouragement combined with the dissatisfaction of a Europe dominated by France as well as the French invasion of Spain, led Austria to join Great Britain in the Fifth Coalition.<SPACE/>The main theater of war was the Danube. The Austrian main army was commanded by her best general, Francis’ brother, Archduke Charles (Karl).  In April, Charles invaded Bavaria only to be stymied by the French general on the spot, Marshal Davout, and then defeated by Napoleon in a series of battles known collectively as Abensburg-Eckmuhl. This defeat forced Charles to withdraw to the north bank of the Danube, leaving Vienna to be occupied for a second time by the French.<SPACE/>On May 22, Napoleon began to cross his army to the north bank of the Danube between the towns of Aspern and Essling. This led to a desperate battle that lasted for two days and resulted in the defeat and withdrawal of the French to the south bank. Aspern-Essling, as the battle came to be known, was Napoleon’s first clear-cut defeat in Europe.<SPACE/>On the other fronts, an Austrian army invaded the Kingdom of Italy, but after an initial success was defeated and forced to retreat north of the Alps. Another Austrian army moved into the Duchy of Warsaw, defeating the Polish army. Finally, Austria encouraged a revolt in the Alpine province of the Tyrol, which had been ceded to Bavaria in 1805. <SPACE/>By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder.<SPACE/>That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat.<SPACE/>After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Francis sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="LODIB">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition along with Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera coast between Genoa and Nice, and had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula. Then in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign, launched one month later in April, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war.<SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands, and this forced Napoleon to conduct a formal siege. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault. Thus, Napoleon was forced into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austria-Hungary Empire, the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of  Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty,  Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France.  The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close.Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather.By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder.That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat.After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Francis sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="LODIC">
      <STRING>Despite the loss of the Austrian Netherlands (Belgium), the defeat of the Dutch Republic, and the reverses on the Rhine, Austria continued the war of the First Coalition. The Coalition included Britain and a number of minor states, including Piedmont, Savoy, and the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. By the spring of 1796, the First Coalition had confined the French Army of Italy to the French and Italian Riviera between Genoa and Nice. They had every expectation of expelling the French from the Italian peninsula when, in March 1796, General Napoleon Bonaparte was appointed to command the French Army of Italy. In a lightning campaign launched one month later, Napoleon defeated the divided Austrian-Piedmontese army and burst into the rich Po River valley. By the end of May, the Austrian army had been driven from the Po, Milan had been captured, and Piedmont forced from the war. <SPACE/>Yet the fortress city of Mantua remained in Austrian hands. Located in the midst of a marsh, Mantua was impregnable to direct assault, which forced Napoleon into a prolonged siege. The Austrian advances to relieve the city and push the French out of the Po valley defined the military operations though early 1797. During this period Napoleon remained on the strategic defensive, fighting and winning the battles of Castiglione, Arcola, and Rivoli.<SPACE/>Mantua finally surrendered in February 1797. This freed Napoleon to invade and capture Venice and Lombardy, and then advance to control the Alps passes which led to the heart of the Austrian Empire—the Danube valley and the imperial capital of Vienna.<SPACE/>This precipitated negotiations that eventually led to the Treaty of Campo Formio, which ratified the preliminary Peace of Leoben, signed at the conclusion of  Bonaparte’s Italian campaign. In the treaty,  Austria ceded its possessions in the Low Countries (the present-day Belgium) to France and secretly promised France the left bank of the Rhine. The Republic of Venice was dissolved and partitioned; all Venetia east of the Adige, as well as Istria and Dalmatia, passed to Austria; the present provinces of Bergamo and Brescia went to the newly founded Cisalpine Republic; and the Ionian Islands went to France.  The treaty also marked the end of the First Coalition and for all intents and purposes also brought the wars of the Revolution to a close.Despite this, Prussia did not capitulate. Its remaining forces retreated east to Poland where they were reinforced by the Russian army. By December the French army was besieging Konigsberg, and had advanced deep into the Prussian-occupied Polish provinces. On December 26 the French army bumped up against the Russians at Putulsk and Golymin. Although the Russians retreated the next day, Napoleon decided to place his army in garrison for the winter. The Russians had other ideas, however, and their advance in the middle of the winter precipitated the battle of Eylau on February 7-8, 1807. After two days of heavy fighting the Russians withdrew, and the French returned to their winter quarters to await better weather.By early July 1809, Napoleon was prepared to cross the Danube and attack Charles in his position opposite Vienna. To maximize his odds for victory Napoleon had ordered his stepson Eugene to march to his assistance with the Army of Italy. On July 4, 1809, the French Army crossed the Danube and launched an immediate attack on the Austrian positions, but night and confusion caused the French to withdraw in disorder.That night, Napoleon ordered Marshal Davout to attack the Austrian left flank and dislodge them from the heights behind the Russbach. At the same time, the Archduke Charles was planning an attack against the French left. What occurred was the most costly two-day battle in the history of the Napoleonic Wars, with the Austrians and French each suffering 40,000 casualties. In the end, however, Charles lost the battle and was forced to retreat.After protracted negotiations, Austria signed the Treaty of Vienna which called for its withdrawal from the Fifth Coalition as well as the ceding of additional provinces to Bavaria, Saxony and the Kingdom of Italy. Austria also agreed to follow the Continental System, by embargoing trade with Britain, and to restrict the size of its army and pay France 85 million francs. Finally, Francis sanctioned the marriage of his daughter Marie Louise to Napoleon, thus becoming his father-in-law. </STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="LODI2">
      <STRING>After Napoleon's first successful campaign in Italy in 1797, he went back there again in 1800 upon assuming control of France as First Consul. Austria had broken the treaty of Campo Formio, which had been negotiated by Napoleon, and declared war on France while Napoleon was in Egypt. In response, Napoleon marched into Italy and defeated the Austrian army at the Battle of Marengo, giving France control of most of Italy. It was after this battle that peace was made with both Austria and Britain, in the treaties of Luneville and Amiens, respectively.</STRING>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GUERRILLA BASES">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="GUERRILLA WARFARE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="TRANSYLVANIA">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="REVOLT">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="INTRO">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="HIDEAWAY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="ROYALIST HIDEAWAY">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="NOMAD">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="DESERT TREK">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="RATIONSR">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="RATIONST">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="SUPPLY TRAIN">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="BATTLE OF TIVOLI2">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
    <ENTRY name="FIELD BATTLE">
      <STRING/>
    </ENTRY>
  </CUSTOM>
  <INSTRUCTIONS name="FRENCH">Priorities:<BULLET/>You are Napoleon Bonaparte, a young officer in the French army. Previously unknown, after your last victory you have been offered a choice of two commands by the Directorate, the council that governs France. Choose wisely, as the one you do not pick will be given to another ambitious officer; the Army of the West - take command of the army based in Paris and attack the French Royalists who have revolted in Burgundy; or the Army of Italy - take command of the army based in Marseilles and attack the Sardinians, vassals of the Austrians, in Piedmont.<SPACE/>Victory Condition:<BULLET/>Win by controlling all of Europe through conquest and diplomacy.<SPACE/>Napoleon Rules:<BULLET/>Becoming Emperor - You must win six territories in order to crown yourself emperor. Before that you will have limited choice of where you attack and little control over diplomatic negotiations.<BULLET/>Napoleon - You start every battle with the Napoleon unit. He grants special bonuses to units in his radius. Select him in battle to find out what bonuses he provides.<BULLET/>Generals - Gain special general cards that can be used as special general units in a battle. Some also can be held for a special bonus or played on the strategic map for a benefit.<BULLET/>Vassals - They count as your territory, but you do not receive rare resource income from them. You do not receive wonder powers from any wonders the vassal nation may control. These nations are not defeated, and as such can escape from your control.<BULLET/>Colonies - These are similar to territories, except that they do not appear on the map and do not contain bonus cards. Instead they provide rare resources, Wonders, and Tribute which is received every turn.<BULLET/>Battle Icons - The crossed swords that appear next to scenario titles are indicative of historical battles.<BULLET/>No Patriots - You do not receive Patriots from your Senate as their place has been taken by Napoleon.</INSTRUCTIONS>
  <INTRO_TEXT>
    <ENTRY name="INTRO_TEXT">The French Revolution<BULLET/>The French Revolution began with the storming of the Bastille in Paris on July 14, 1789. The large middle class of France was no longer willing to take orders from the established elite. Many had begun criticizing the noblemen and clergy, and what propelled the crisis was the severe economic hardship in France in the 1780s. The monarchy of old was not providing the support needed by the middle class, and they were fed up with the king, Louis XVI. He tried to reform the economic structure of France, but it was too late. The king gathered troops in Paris, but crowds began taking to the street, and when the Bastille was stormed the king removed the troops in Paris rather than have them fight the crowds.<BULLET/>By August a National Assembly had written the "Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen", which they hoped would translate into a new constitution. The document included provisions for property rights, freedom of speech, and personal security. It also decreed that the power to rule derived from the people, not from the king. Louis was still frightened, and approved the declaration. A new constitution was approved, taking away the privileges that had been formerly granted to the elite and instead giving equal rights to all. This led to many of the former elite fleeing to foreign countries and trying to get them to intervene in France. <SPACE/>Political Climate in Europe<BULLET/>As the French Revolution became more radical, Prussia and Austria formed a defensive alliance for their mutual protection, known as the First Coalition. On April 20, 1792, the French Assembly voted for war against Austria in order to “free” their fellow man from tyranny. Britain joined the coalition after the execution of Louis XVI in January 1793 and Spain followed in March. France in turn declared war on the Dutch Republic and soon after Russia joined the coalition.<BULLET/>In July 1793, the combined Prussian-Austrian army achieved a major victory over France. Then, before the campaigning season began in the spring 1794, a general revolt occurred in Prussia’s Polish provinces. Forced to redirect not only its army but also its resources, Prussia could no longer bring any offensive action against France in 1794. In April 1795, Prussia signed the Treaty of Basel, in which France agreed not to attack Prussian territory and Prussia agreed to withdraw from the First Coalition. Spain followed suit by agreeing to peace with France on April 22, 1795. The Dutch Republic was very quickly overrun and France then created the Batavian Republic in its place. With so much chaos both at home and abroad, France was left open for a strong individual to step in and become a legend.<SPACE/>Napoleon's Early Military Career<BULLET/>Napoleon’s involvement in the French army began when he was sent off to the French military academy at Brienne in 1779. He returned to Corsica after graduating, but civil war in Corsica caused his family to flee back to France, where Napoleon rejoined the French army. Napoleon’s first success in the army happened when he took command of several units in Avignon to put down a revolt, and in Toulon where he took command of a siege unit to fight off the British ships off the coast. His friend, General Paul Barras, next placed him in charge of the defense of Paris, where Napoleon defended the Tuileries against an aggravated mob with “a whiff of grapeshot”. It was after this victory that Napoleon was put in charge of the Army of Italy, and began his string of great victories for France.</ENTRY>
  </INTRO_TEXT>
</ROOT>
